<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly, zealous and learned sermon vpon the 18. 19. 20. 21. verses of the 10. chap. to the Romaines. Wherein is set foorth vnto vs the greate mercy of God in the calling of the Gentiles, and his iust iudgement in the reiecting of the vnbeleeuing Iewes, &amp; vs also, if vve vvith like obstinancie contemne his profered mercies. By Frauncis Tayler preacher of Gods word.</title>
            <author>Tayler, Francis, preacher.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100546</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836383</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">651</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13407)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 651)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1366:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly, zealous and learned sermon vpon the 18. 19. 20. 21. verses of the 10. chap. to the Romaines. Wherein is set foorth vnto vs the greate mercy of God in the calling of the Gentiles, and his iust iudgement in the reiecting of the vnbeleeuing Iewes, &amp; vs also, if vve vvith like obstinancie contemne his profered mercies. By Frauncis Tayler preacher of Gods word.</title>
                  <author>Tayler, Francis, preacher.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. D[awson] for Thomas Woodcocke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1583.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A(-A1) B-C.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon of the Gentiles called and the Iewes reiected.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through and some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:651:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:651:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Godly, zealous and learned <hi>Sermon, vpon the</hi> 18.19.20.21. verſes of the 10. Chap. to the Romaines.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſet foorth vnto vs <hi>the greate mercy of God in the</hi> calling of the Gentiles, and his iuſt iudgement in the reiecting of the vnbeleeuing Iewes, &amp; vs alſo, if we with like obſtinacie contemne his profered mercies.</p>
            <p>By Frauncis Tayler <hi>Preacher of Gods word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Jmprinted at</hi> London by T.D. for Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas <hi>Woodcocke.</hi> 1583.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:651:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:651:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ver.</hi> 18.</bibl> BVt I demaund, haue they not hearde? No doubte their ſounde went out through all the earth, and their words into the endes of the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>19</bibl> But I demand, did not Iſrael know God? Firſt, Moſes ſaith, I will prouoke you to enuy by a natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is not my nation, and by a fooliſhe nation will I anger you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>20</bibl> And Eſaias is bold and ſaith, I was found of them that ſought me not, &amp; haue byn made manifeſt to them that aſked not after me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>21</bibl> And vnto Iſrael he ſaith, all the day long, haue I ſtretched foorth my hand vnto a diſobedient and gainſaying people.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the beginning of this Epiſtle, but chiefly from the beginning of the <hi>9.</hi> Chapter, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle began to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Gods eternal prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination,
<pb facs="tcp:651:3"/>which is the firſt cauſe of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, we haue heard, howe many wayes Paules aduerſaries (but chiefly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes) haue ſet themſelues againſt him: but aboue the reſt the Iewes are greeued with that which Paule had written of the reieccing of the Iewes and calling of the Gentiles, and to ſhewe that his doctrine heerein can not ſtande, they examyne his laſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and thereout they gather (as they thinke) ſufficient matter for them ſelues, to prooue that they are not caſt off from GOD, nor the Gentiles choſen to bee Gods Church.</p>
            <p>The laſt argument or reaſon which the Apoſtle hath vſed, is from the beginning of the <hi>13.</hi> verſe, it doth ſtand vpon certaine degrees, and may bee layde foorth thus: To ſerue God rightly is a teſtimonye of true faith, to beleeue truly is a deelaration of an effectuall calling, to bee called ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually doth well proue a certayne elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: but the Gentiles doe ſerue GOD aright and therefore they beleeue, they beleeue, and therefore are called, they are called, and therfore elected vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:651:3"/>
            <p>Now vppon this argument of Paule, the Iewes do thinke to proue their owne elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more certaine then the election of the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, &amp; one thing they lay for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, whereupon all theſe degrees ſee downe by Paule in part, doe ſtand, and which aboue the reſt doth ſeame to be very manifeſt on their ſide, and that is this that they haue had the woorde: as if they ſhoulde ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paule: Thou wilt proue the election of the Gentiles by that they haue faith, the ſeruice of God, &amp; calling to the knowledge and grace of GOD, and thou doeſt tell vs that all thoſe doe come by bearing the woorde preached: and why then do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou ſaye that the Iewes are reiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? Haue they not hearde? Yes Sir the Iewes had the lawe and the vſe thereof aboue fifteene hundred yeeres before it was publiſhed to the Gentiles: the Iewes had Prophetes to expounde the lawe vnto them, and to plant in their heartes fayth in that Sauiour which was to come, the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles had no prophets vnles at a time ſome one were ſent vnto them extraordinarily.
<pb facs="tcp:651:4"/>The Iewes had the ſauiour of the worlde borue not onely among them, but of their owne fleſh, he did preach among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much more then among the Gentiles: yea, &amp; the diſciples themſelues did firſt preach vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, &amp; were much more careful to make Chriſt knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them, then they were to make him knowen vnto the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>For Chriſt himſelfe being a miniſter of the circumciſion,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.8.</note> did at the firſt forbid his diſciples to goe vnto the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.5.</note> &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to goe to the loſt ſheepe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Iſrael, which were the Iewes, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement they did wel obſerue and keepe?<note place="margin">Act. 13.46.</note> as may appeare as well by that that Paule and Barnabas do confeſſe they were firſt ſent vnto the Iewes, and for that cauſe had firſt preached vnto them, as alſo by that all the Apoſtlee at Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were grieuouſly offended with Peter for that he went and preached the word to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his family which were Gentiles:<note place="margin">Act. 11.2.</note> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king indeede that Peter had done a thing vnlawfull, and which might not poſſiblye ſtand with Gods will and lyking.</p>
            <p>To bring now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the Iewes do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb facs="tcp:651:4"/>againſt Paule into few wordes, thus they ſay in effect: Where God doth ſend his word to be preached, there God hath a Church and people whom he will call to the knowledge of his will, to faith in him, and to his true ſeruice and obedience: but God hath ſent his worde to be preached to the Iewes, more then to the Gentiles, as is proued, and therefore God hath his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes, rather then among the Gentiles: yea and wil be knowen, beleeued on, ſerued, &amp; obeyed of the Iewes rather then of the Gentiles. And this argument the Iewes thinke that Paule can by no meanes auoyd, but either he muſt deny his owne words going before, to be true, or els he muſt needes ſaye the Iewes haue not heard, and becauſe they ſuppoſe he wil not deny his owne woordes, therefore this is the only queſtion they aſke, as the Apoſtle himſelfe in their perſon doth ſet it downe? <hi>Haue they not heard?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus then we ſee the occaſion of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the Iewes againſt Paul, &amp; wher upon it is grounded: now let vs ſee Pauls auſwere. No doubt their ſoſid we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t through
<pb facs="tcp:651:5"/>all the earth, and their wordes into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ends of the world. Theſe words are truely eited out of the Prophet Dauid. <hi>Pſal. 19. ver. 3.</hi> The wordes are two wayes to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Firſt, in what ſenſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet Dauid did ſpeake them, and ſecondly to what end the Apoſtle Paule doth cite them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> For the Prophet Dauid, he going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to moue the people to a deep conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods benefits, that thereby they might the better promote gods glory, doth ſet before them the workmanſhip of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and the world, and doth cell them that the line, ſquare, or proportion thereof doth ſet foorth vnto them the woorthines of the Creator, &amp; for as much as this proportion &amp; frame is ſeene of all men, therefore it ought to ſtirre vp all men to a greater ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forwarde of Gods glory: this frame &amp; proportion the Grecians call a ſound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the excellencie of ſo greate a woorke doeth preach, and as it were, ſpeake in the eares of all men, the knowledge of God to the better ſetting foorth of Gods prayſe and glory: So then the woordes of Dauid tell vs thus much: that GOD hath ſet
<pb facs="tcp:651:5"/>foorth the certayne gouernment, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and order of all the worlde to all men, Iewes and Gentiles &amp; whatſoeuer, to the end that in theſe thinges God may be knowen and glorified according to his will: as for example. The erection of theſe thinges doth teache vs that GOD is omnipotent, and therefore muſt be obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The diſpoſition, order, and gouernment of theſe thinges doe tel vs that God is wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and therefore wee muſt be content to be ruled by his lawes and ſtatutes.</p>
            <p>The woonderfull preſeruing and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them doth let vs ſee that he is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, and therefore we muſt truſt in him. The manie and ſtraunge puniſhmentes which God doeth ſend among men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee vppon their owne bodies and myndes, vpon their goodes and cattayles, or otherwiſe howſoeuer, doth preach vnto vs the iuſtice of God, and tell vs that hee muſt be feared. And generally, the inuiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things of him, that is,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> his eternal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and godhead are ſeene by the creation of the world, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in his works. And this it is that GOD will ceache vs
<pb facs="tcp:651:6"/>when telling vs how we ſhal put differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betweene the true God and falſe gods he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aith: Lift vp your eyes on hye,<note place="margin">Eſay 40.26.</note> &amp; behold who hath made theſe things, and bringeth forth their armies by number &amp; calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al by their names: as if he ſhould ſay, if you wil diſcerne betwixt the true God &amp; your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfet gods, &amp; if you wil learn to know the true God indeed, look vpon his works, the heauens, the earth, and al the world, ſee in them his power, wiſedome, mercy and iuſtice, and learne by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to performe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that ſeruice and obedience which is due. But it may be ſaid, what if the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles wil not? Or what if any other wil not learn to confeſſe and feare the true God by theſe things, what is the danger? Verily the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is this, It doth make their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without excuſe, ſo that nowe if they would ſay, we could not ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true God, becauſe we did not know him, their owne conſcience ſhall tell them that the inuiſible things of god are manifeſted in his works, for their ſound went out into al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth &amp;c. I ſay not that this knowledge of God by his creatures is ſufficient vnto ſaluation,
<pb facs="tcp:651:6"/>for to ſaluation there is required ſuche a knowledge as doth bring faith in Chriſt, &amp; teach vs obedience to his will, and this knowledge is only by his worde: but this I ſay, that we haue by Gods creatures ſo much knowledge of God as is fufficient to condemne vs by very iuſtice if it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, ſo that if the wicked would preſume &amp; ſeeke to reuerſe Gods iudgementes as vniuſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note> yet euen by this ſhold God be found iuſt in his ſayinges, and pure in his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And leaſt I ſhoulde barely affirme this as mine own opinion without proofe: the Apoſtle Paul doth teache vs the ſame vſe and end of this doctrine: for when hee ſayth that his power and godhead are kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen by the exeation of the world, he addeth that it is to this intent that they ſhoulde be without exeuſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And to this doth agree that whiche is written in the booke of wiſedome:<note place="margin">Sap. 13.8, 9.</note> They are not to be excuſed, for if they can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the worlde, why doe they not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther finde out the Lorde thereof? I might bring this from the heathen and ſuche as haue no knowledge of GOD but by his
<pb facs="tcp:651:7"/>creatures to our ſelues which haue the vſe of his worde, and it would very well meet with the opinion of the wieked, whiche thinke to pleade ignoraunce againſt Gods iudgementes, for when they haue no taſte of gods mercies, no feeling of Chriſt, none aſſuraunce of their ſaluation by fayth: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſeeke to goe to heauen by bywayes, and they will be ſaued (forſooch) by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Saintes, by pardons from men, by treneales, and ſuch like things as inſideliry hach deuiſed for inan vainly to flatter him ſelfe in: and when theſe things are founde to be deuices of men, then they muſt be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by their good works, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al other ſhifees faile, yet at woorſt they will not bee puniſhed, for they ſay ignorance ſhal excuſe them, but ſee how herein they are decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. For if ignorance cannot ercuſe thoſe which haue none other knowledge of God then by his creatures, but that their conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhal be without excuſe, muche leſſe may it be an excuſe to thoſe which haue not only y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſight of his creatures, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of his word. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſins co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, are not therefore excuſable, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:651:7"/>they are done ignorantly, it may thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.<note place="margin">Leuit. 5.17. Num. 15.22.</note>There were in the lawe ſacrifices appointed to be offered for thoſe ſins whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che were committed of ignorance. <hi>Haba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuck</hi> doth pray for ſuch ſinnes.<note place="margin">Haba. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> And Chriſt himſelfe doth tel vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as well thoſe which are blind in the knowledge of his word,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.14.</note> as thoſe which ſee ſhal fal into the ditch of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (if they continue in ſinne.) When Paul had preached at Corinth a yeere and a halfe, and had written vnto them one E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, he ſent them word in the next epiſtle, that they ſhoulde not thinke it a ſufficient excuſe, that they could ſay we are ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but he doth tel them that if now they be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt, it is a manifeſt proofe that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than doeth rule in them,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.2.</note> but for as muche (ſaith he) as we now handle the worde of God truely, and for proofe thereof wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to euery mans conſcience in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God, therfore, if our Goſpel be now hid, it is hid in them that are loſt, in whom the God of this world hath blinded the mynds of the Infidel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es that the light of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goſpell of Chriſt whiche is the image of God ſhoulde not ſhyne vnto them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:651:8"/>
            <p>Let vs not then thinke to pleade igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it will not ſerue: if the Corinthians were ſo farre from being excuſed by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that it was a teſtimony y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were vnder the gouernment of Sathan when y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Goſpel had byn publiſhed among them but a ſmall time, much more ſhal it teſtifie the ſame vnto vs whiche haue had the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel preached amongſt vs a great deale lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time: well then take theſe words as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet Dauid did ſpeak and meane the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and they teach vs thus much: That the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of Gods creatures doth preach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the power, wiſedome, mercy, &amp; iuſtice of him that made them, &amp; therfore nowe if we doe not acknowledge him to be God &amp; worſhip &amp; obey him as God, we are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe: but much more inexcuſable we are if we doe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame when we haue the word preached, yea, &amp; the more the word is preached amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greater &amp; more iuſt is our conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, if we doe not beleeue &amp; followe the ſame word. And thus much of theſe wordes vs they are to hee vnderſtood in the Pſalme.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> The ſecond thing whiche I ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:651:8"/>was to be conſidered in theſe wordes is, to what end the Apoſtle doth cite them. And when I make difference betwixt the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Dauid &amp; Paul in theſe wordes, I meane not that there is any contradiction or contrary meaning in them: but only that Paule taking the wordes of Dauid, doth cite them as it were to a larger ſenſe then Dauid did ſpeake them, as very well he might. And the difference is but this, that Dauid doth ſay that the creatures of God, haue preached God vnto al men, and Paul doth affirme in the ſame words, that God hath been manifeſted by his worde to the Iewes, and to very many other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries beſide: as if hee ſhoulde ſay, euen as Dauid in his time did affirme, that God had beene then preached to all people by his creatures: So I ſay of this time (ſaith Paule) that God hath been publiſhed and taught in all places by the preaching of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel. And therfore where ye aſke me this queſtion: <hi>Haue they not heard?</hi> I eaſily graunt that they haue heard, for no doubt their ſounde went out through al the earth, &amp;c. This the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb facs="tcp:651:9"/>Paule doth cite this teſtimonie of Dauid, to ſhew that the Iewes haue hard the woorde: and hee doeth proue it thus, the goſpel hath beene preached to all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ergo to the Iewes: or thus, The Goſpel hath beene preached vnto the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, I cannot denie it, but much more muſt I needes confeſſe, it hath been prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to the Iewes. This then is Pauls anſwere if we take it largely as hee doth ſpeake it: The goſpell hath nowe had ſuche good ſucceſſe, that it hath beene preached in all Countries: and the ſound of the Apoſtles hath ben heard almoſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where.</p>
            <p>In the general wordes of this anſwere we haue firſt to note, the great increaſe of the goſpell in the time of the Apoſtles, when although it was not receiued by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> like authoritie of the Romane Empyre, yet although it was almoſt euery where (not only ſpoken againſt, but alſo perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted) yet Paule doth confeſſe of himſelfe.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.19.</note>that hee hath preached the goſpell plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully from Ieruſalem to Illyricum, and the ſtorie of the Acces of the Apoſtles
<pb facs="tcp:651:9"/>doth deelare that in that time the goſpeli was preached as farre as from Italie to the Medes and Perſians one way, and as farre as from Egypt to Pontus, an other way. And this was nothing els, but that which Chriſte himſelfe had tolde them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when ſpeaking of the ſignes that ſhoulde goe before the deſtruction of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, he ſaith:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.14.</note> And this goſpell of the kingdome ſhall bee preached in the whole worlde for a teſtimonie to all nations, and then ſhall the ende come. There be ſome which gather vpon this place, that the worlde ſhall not haue an ende vntyll the Goſpell bee preached in all Countries: But they deceiue themſelues in putting no difference betwixt thoſe things which are ſpoken of the end of the world, &amp; thoſe which are ſpoken of the ouerthrow of the Citie and temple of Ieruſalem: as for this place it is euident, it is ment not of the end of the world, but of theend and deſtruction of the Citie, and chiefly, of the Temple. For of thoſe the queſtion was chiefly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, as may appeare. <hi>Mat. 24. ver. 3.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Ther fore when it is ſaid that the goſpel ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:651:10"/>preached in all the world, and then the end ſhall come. It is as much as if he ſhould haue ſaide, it ſhall be preached not only to the Iewes, but alſo to the Gentiles, yea, &amp; to a great part of the Gentiles, and then ſhall come the end and deſtruction of this Temple. And this it is which Paul doth tell the Colloſſians:<note place="margin">Colloſ. 1.6</note> That the Goſpel is come vnto them, euen as it is vnto all the worlde. And vnto Timothie, God is manifeſted in the fleſh,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.16.</note> iuſtified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſpirite, ſeene of angels, preached vnto the Gentiles, beleeued on in the worlde. All theſe thinges were done in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, and ſo it is both fulfilled which Chriſte dyd foretell, that the Goſpel ſhold bee preached both to the Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyles, and to a great part of the worlde, before the deſtruction of Ieruſalem: and alſo found true which the Apoſtle Paule here doth tel vs, that in his time the ſound of the Goſpell by the preaching of the Apoſtles, was gone out through the moſt part of the worlde. Beholde heere one of the greateſt myracles that God hath wrought: namely, that (in the ſpace of
<pb facs="tcp:651:10"/>twentie two yeeres or there aboute) the Goſpel ſhould bee ſo farre publiſhed, that Paule might truely ſay, the ſound thereof went through out all the earth, &amp;c. And that by men of no great account in their owne countrie, but fiſher men, or of ſome handie craft: ſuch as were generally (&amp; as it were) naturally hated in all other coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, becauſe they were Iewes: And for the better manifeſting of this myracle, let it bee added, they did preach nothing but Chriſte crucified, which before was not hearde of, and (as the Apoſtle himſelf doth teſtifie) was an offence to the Iewes and meere madneſſe to the Gentyles. Let vs heere learne for our inſtruction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: that the planting or continuing of the Goſpel in any country is not in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of man, but in the wyll of God: and though wee ſee the Pope, the Turke, the Diuel, and all his friendes bente a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the Goſpell, and laying theyr heades togeather to ſtoppe the courſe thereof in all places, yet let vs not thinke that it is in the power of theſe to doe it. It is the onely woorke of God
<pb facs="tcp:651:11"/>to proſper or to ſtaye it: and therefore in this caſe let vs not feare ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe breath is in his noſe thrils; and in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is no ſtrength (in compariſon of God.) But let vs pray vnto God for the continuaunce of his woorde, and nowe that wee haue it, let vs receiue it thankfully, heare it diligently, and obey it duetifully. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes knowing this, that the continuing of the goſpell is the worke of God, and not of man: the ſtaying and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the ſame, is the worke of GOD, and not of man, and God will continue it vntyll hee bee compelled to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie by our vnthankfulneſſe, and then hee muſt and wyll take it awaye. And if the Pope and his holy conſpiracie wyll vowe the baniſhing of the Goſpell out of all Realmes and Countries, where it is nowe preached, and the planting of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie in the ſame Countries, this vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall publiſhyng of the Goſpell in Paules time, will tell them that in row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of this ſtone they labour invayne: For though they make accounte that they bee Princes, and great Peeres
<pb facs="tcp:651:11"/>of the worlde, yet in as muche as they conſulte agaynſt the Lorde and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted:<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note>Hee that dwelleth in heauen will laugh them to ſcorne, yet the Lord hym ſelfe wyll haue them in deriſion: yea, and in deſpite of them the goſpell muſt ſtoryſh where, and as long as God ſhall thinke good.</p>
            <p>The doctrine of gods worde is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a ſtorme or to rayne,<note place="margin">Deut. 32.2. Eſay. 55.10. Heb. 6.7.</note> not onelie becauſe it doth water and make fruitfull the heartes of men, as rayne doth the earth, but alſo becauſe as it is not in man to forbyd a ſhowre to fall where GOD hath appoynted it. no more is it in man to ſtoppe the courſe of the goſpel, where God hath appointed that it ſhall bee prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: It may goe for an olde wiues Fable, and (as it is) for an vnwritten vntrueth, that they tell vs: that Thomas Becket ſtoode ſo farre in our Ladyes fauour, that if he had lyued but a litle longer, hee had obtayned that it neuer ſhoulde rayne in the hyghe wayes in Englande. Thomas coulde not doe it, it is a lye, no if all the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:651:12"/>woulde take this matter in hand to ſtoppe raine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould not fall in any place, they can not doe it: and euen as vnpoſſible it is that by the authoritie or pollicie of man, the courſe of Gods worde ſhal be ſtopped, but that it ſhall goe foorth and proſper in that where to it is ſent: to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of vs and all others, where the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell nowe is preached, and to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt bewraying of theyr great folly, and wickedneſſe, which ſet themſelues againſt God in this point.</p>
            <p>But from the generall woordes, let vs come a little neerer to the very purpoſe of Paule. His aduerſaries aſke of hym, Why doeſt thou ſay, that the Iewes are reiected? Where haue they not hearde the worde preached? Yes in deede (ſaith Paule) they haue hearde, it cannot bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, for the ſounde went foorth through all the earth &amp;c. The Gentiles haue hearde muche more, the Iewes amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt whome the worde beganne firſt, and was continued vntill the Iewes liued in ſuch contempt of the woorde that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples were in a maner co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to go to
<pb facs="tcp:651:12"/>the Gentiles, as they them ſelues confeſſe.<note place="margin">Act. 13.46.</note>The Apoſtle then doth confeſſe, that the Iewes haue hearde the worde, but yet it muſt ſtande that they are reiected? And ſo his very purpoſe is to giue them ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vnderſtande, that the cauſe why the Iewes were reiected, was, not becauſe they had not the vſe of the worde, but bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned the ſame word which they had, as if he ſhould haue ſayde: the Iewes in deede had the word, it was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched among them, but yet God hath in iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice cutte them off, becauſe they deſpiſed the word. And here the Apoſtle will haue vs to learne not onelye what was the cauſe of the cutting off of the Iewes, but alſo he will lay before vs a great cauſe of gods anger, and of many plagues which in all ages fall vpon men, and that is the contempt of his worde. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth more argue a childe to be diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and careleſſe to doe his Fathers will, then when hee hath no minde to knowe what his Fathers will is, nor to heare his admonitions: And there is nothing doth more euidentlye proue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious
<pb facs="tcp:651:13"/>and diſobedient minde in maſt, then when hee hath no care to heare Gods will reuealed in his word, nor to knowe what it is. There is nothing that God hath more care of, then that his worde ſhall not be deſpyſed, neyther any ſinne which god hath more ſeuerely puniſhed at all tymes, then the contempt of his worde, as the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of all ages will tell vs: This nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no great proofe, this preſent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which the Apoſtle here hath in hande will make it plaine enough.</p>
            <p>The Iewes had the lawe giuen vnto them, they had Prophetes ſent to preach and expound the lawe, they had Chriſt and his Apoſtles to preache and worke myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, to call them to ſaluation in the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias which was come, they deſpyſed the Lawe, they perſecuted and killed the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of their ſaluation. And therefore the Apoſtle here ſaieth: (notwithſtanding that they had the word) yet god hath caſte them off, becauſe they were contemners of the word, and would not willingly obey it, no not ſo much as heare it.</p>
            <p>But that this may bee proſitable to vs,
<pb facs="tcp:651:13"/>let vs bring it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes to our ſelues, and let vs not deceiue our ſelues by promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelues, that the hearing of his worde is eyther a matter that God doeth make ſmall account of, or elſe, that in that ſlacke hearing which we vſe, wee doe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently anſwere Gods expectation here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For in fewe wordes it is thus with vs and no better: there is nothing that God doeth more eſteeme then his worde, there is nothing, which wee more contemne. Say to a man, ſir ye ought not to lyue in this or that ſinn, it is wicked, it is contrary to Gods word, your vſury, your trauailing on the Sabboth day, your blaſpheming of gods name, and ſuch like, they are forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſcripture, his common aunſwer is: can you ſhe we vs any ſtatute againſt theſe things? is there any lawe in force, whiche doth forbid them? if there bee a ſtatute that may be ſome ſtay, if not,<note place="margin">Exod. 5.2.</note> though al his lyfe be directly againſt gods law, he careth not. And is not this to ſay with Pharao? What is the Lord that I ſhould heare his voice, and ſette Iſrael goe. I knowe not the Lorde, I will not let Iſrael goe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:651:14"/>
            <p>Agayne, tel another of his negligence in hearing the word, it is an ordinary anſwer, if we had preaching but according to the Queenes Iniunctions, one Sermon in a moneth, or in a quarter of a yeare, then we ſhould be the more diligent to heare, but nowe it is two dayes in a weeke, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs wearie. Is not this to ſay with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael: Our ſtumack doth loath this lyght meate?<note place="margin">Num. 11.</note> But <hi>Pharao</hi> had his rewarde for contemning of the worde, and ſo had Iſrael, and no doubt ſo ſhal we, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the ſame contempt, wherein wee haue begunne, and of long time haue gone forward. Let vs learne in what ſtate wee ſtande, by the example of the Iewes, of whome Paule here ſpeaketh: compare our time and manners with theirs, and ſo it ſhall beſt appeare: They were Gods Vineyarde, ſo be we, they were digged, pruned and dreſſed by the preaching of the worde, and good gouernment, ſo bee wee. they were deſpiſers and negligent hearers of the word, ſo be we: For this cauſe they had this iudgemente:<note place="margin">Math. 21.43.</note> The kingdome of God ſhall be taken away from you, and
<pb facs="tcp:651:14"/>giuen to a nation, which ſhall bring forth the fruites therof: and I pray GOD the like fall not vpon vs.<note place="margin">Act. 13.46</note> And when Paule and Barnabas had preached to the Iewes, and they had no care to heare, at length they take theyr leaue thus: It was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that the word of God ſhould firſte be ſpoken vnto you: but ſeeing you put it from you, and iudge your ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of eternal life, beholde we turne to the Gentiles. Thus it was with the Iewes, this was their contempte of the worde, thus God did threaten them, and thus it came to paſſe. Let vs learne by their example to auoyd the like contempte of his word, leaſt the like puniſhment fall vpon vs. God is the ſame God now that he was then, iuſtice is the ſame thing now that it was then, the contempt or neglecte of Gods word is now the ſame ſinne that it was then. And therefore if wee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in the contempt of God and his word, as they did, no doubt wee ſhall haue the like puniſhment as they had: that is, to haue the word taken from vs, and gyuen to a nation, which will bringe forth the
<pb facs="tcp:651:15"/>fruite thereof: for myne owne part, I pray God I may not ſee it, but God knoweth, I looke for it: And I doubte not but (when this time ſhall come, which God defend) a number of thoſe which now loath the word wil then lacke it: we feede now at the full heape (God be thanked for it) wee haue his word at wil, yeaeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> til we be weary of it, eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pecially in towns hereabout, we haue time giuen vs to aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble our ſelues in prayer to God, and to receiue the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper, a great deale more then we will beſtow that way: theſe are the dayes of ioy and happineſſe, if we well vſe them. But alas how miſerable ſhall our frate be, if that come to paſſe, which Chriſte doeth threaten to the contemners of his woord.<note place="margin">Luk 17.22</note>The dayes will come, when yee ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee one daye of the Sonne of man, and ſhall not ſee it: Then one Sermon would be pleaſaunt, but you ſhal not heare it: Then one day to aſſemble in prayer vnto GOD, and other good exerciſes of Chriſtianitie ſhall be wiſhed for,<note place="margin">Amos. 8.11.</note> but hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye founde: yea, then ſaith God, I will
<pb facs="tcp:651:15"/>ſende a famyne in the Lande, not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne of Bread, nor a thyrſte of Water, but a famyne of hearing the worde of the Lorde, and they ſhall wander from Sea to Sea, and from the North to the Eaſte, ſhall they runne to and froe to ſeeke the worde of the Lorde, and ſhall not finde it. A wiſe man (ſaieth Salomon) doth ſee the plague comming, and doeth auoyde it.<note place="margin">Pro. 22.3.</note>We ſee the greeuouſneſſe of this ſinne of the contempt of Gods worde, wee knowe the iuſtice of God in puniſhing the ſame ſinne. And we can imagine beefore it come to paſſe how miſerable the dayes wil be, if it pleaſe GOD to puniſhe vs with the loſſe of his woorde: Then if wee bee wyſe, let vs take heede, that by our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe wee drawe not this plague vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Let vs turne vnto GOD nowe whyle hee may bee found, let vs kiſſe his Sonne before hee be angry, let vs receiue his word thankfully now it is offered, let vs heare it dutifully, and followe it obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientlye, yea, and let vs not forget to call vppon God diligentlye and earneſtly, that
<pb facs="tcp:651:16"/>it would pleaſe him to continue &amp; increaſe his worde amonge vs, and to thruſt foorth ſuch labourers into his harneſt, as may not ſeeke their owne wealth and pleaſure, but Gods glorye, and the ſaluation of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Alwayes hauing in minde how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable our dayes will bee, if it pleaſe GOD to puniſhe vs with the loſſe of his worde, which no doubt is Gods iuſt iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the contempt of the ſame. But me thinkes I am paſt doubt, that when Chriſte, the Prophetes and Apoſtles doe teach, that the taking away of the worde is a iuſt puniſhment for the contempt therof, the worſt part of the Iewes, whom chiefly it ſhould touche doe like it well enough: Yea and with vs a number of Papiſtes and Atheiſtes are not greeued when they heare of the loſſe of the worde: no they ſay this is that which they looke for: for they make account, that then they ſhall lyue at pleaſure and ſinne without controlment: But knowe they whatſoeuer they be, that God hath other puniſhmentes in ſtore for ſuch as contemne his worde, and take it not for a puniſhment to be depriued of the
<pb facs="tcp:651:16"/>the ſame word, as that which Elihu doeth tell vs: If they will not heare,<note place="margin">Iob. 36.12.</note> they ſhall paſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſword, &amp; die without knowledge: As if he ſhould ſay vnto vs, you are conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the word, and you care not for the loſſe thereof: no you account it gaine ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then loſſe, wel. God hath yet an other puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſtore, the Pope hath a ſword, Spayne hath a ſworde, Fraunce hath a ſworde, the wicked euerye where haue a ſworde ready prepared for your blood, to that you ſhall goe, and vpon that you ſhall die without the knowledge of God. Yea, but you will ſay we be Catholiks, and if this come to paſſe, we will take their part: But I ſay, thinke not to eſcape the better for that: For there is no people ſo ſimple, but they can tell, that thoſe which are not true to their owne natiue Country, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to their own naturall Prince, they wil neuer be true nor obedient vnto ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: And this it is that experience hath taught in al ages: Whenſoeuer any coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey was by the inhabitants thereof dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by treaſon or trecherie, into the handes of the enimie, for the moſte parte,
<pb facs="tcp:651:17"/>thoſe which were the delyuerers were firſt put to the ſword: And I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that, if that day ſhould come, which a number of our Papiſts do looke for, that they them ſelues ſhoulde firſte taſte of the ſworde: It doeth ſtande with Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that as they haue moſte deſpiſed the word, ſo they ſhould firſt feele the ſworde: It ſtandes with pollicye not to truſte the vntruſtie: And let them thinke of this, as God ſhall put in their mindes: for myne owne parte, if I were a Papiſte, and an enemy to God and his worde, as they bee, and did beare a traytorous minde towarde my prince and countrey, as they doe, I ſhould ſurely looke for this reward. Elithu here would tell me, pollicy woulde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, and the conſideration of Gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice would binde me to confeſſe, I am one of thoſe which deſpiſe the worde of God, I muſt therefore be one of them which muſte taſte of that whipp which God doth keepe in ſtore to puniſh this ſinne.</p>
            <p>But let it be that we haue a way to eſcape this rod, yet let vs imagine, if wee wyll that Gods worde in this poynt is not true,
<pb facs="tcp:651:17"/>and that God eyther can not, or els wyll not puniſh vs this way: yet let vs knowe that God is iuſt, and as he did ſeuerely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe this ſinne in the Iewes, ſo hee will alſo ſurely be reuenged of the ſame ſinn in vs: for eyther God will ſend ſtrong deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that we ſhould beleeue lies to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.11.</note>which would not receiue the trueth to our ſaluation, as Paul doth threaten the Theſſalonians: or els hee will giue vs the ſpirit of ſlumber, eies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhall not ſee, &amp; eares, that we ſhould not heare, that is, god will take from vs his ſpirite and grace, and then we ſhal neither beleeue his word. nor haue any deſire to bee obedient to his will, no not if wee woulde deſire: But howſoeuer it is, or howeſoeuer it pleaſe God to puniſh this ſinne: moſte aſſuredly it ſhall ſtande, which the holy Ghoſte hath ſpoken by the mouth of Solomon:</p>
            <p>Hee that deſpyſeth the worde ſhall periſh for it:<note place="margin">Pro. 13.13,</note> but yet we thinke we haue one ſhifte to eſcape this puniſhment, which we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues will deliuer vs, when all other helpes faile, and that is this, we will pray vnto GOD, and hee will delyuer vs
<pb facs="tcp:651:18"/>out of all aduerſitie: he hath promiſed hee will ſurely perfourme it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> And true it is. God hath promyſed to heare and delyuer all thoſe which cal vpon him in their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for hee is nygh to all ſuch as call v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.18</note> ſo it be done in trueth. But if wee will haue our prayers hearde, there bee diuers things which we muſt obſerue in prayer, amonge which this is not the leaſt: Wee muſt take heede that wee be not deſpiſers of his word. For hee that doeth remoue his eare from hearing of the Lawe,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.9.</note> his prayer ſhall be abhommable, ſaith Solomon.</p>
            <p>And this is a greeuous plague, when we are not onely in Gods diſpleaſure, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hee hath depriued vs of thoſe helpes, wherby we ſhould againe be reſtored into his fauour. Wel, it is but thus much that Paule wil haue vs to learne in this point: The Iewes had the worde preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them, but this did not proſit them, becauſe they regarded not, to heare or fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the ſame: If wee make this our owne caſe, it is thus with vs: We haue the word preached, God be thanked for it,
<pb facs="tcp:651:18"/>and I pray God continue it, as no doubt hee wil, if our wickedneſſe do not compell him in iuſtice to take it from vs: But if wee be deſpiſers of his worde, and that ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee bee not carefull to heare it, or diligent to obey it: This worde God wil take from vs, and giue it to ſome other nation, which wil bring forth fruite woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the preaching of this word: And not onely this, but hee will puniſh vs either by the ſworde of our enemies, by hardneſſe of heart, by falling into hereſies and falſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions againſt God, or ſome way as ſhal ſeeme beſt vnto him: And then al our ſhifts ſhal not helpe: No, if wee will ſay with the Iewes, wee haue hearde the worde, wee ſhall haue this anſwere: It is nothing to heare, vnleſſe wee be obedient and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: Yet if we could ſaye: Wee haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyed in thy name, and in thy name haue wee caſt out deuilles, and wrought my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles: yet if this be not ioyned with fayth and obedience, it hath but this rewarde: Departe from me yee workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I know you not.</p>
            <p>It foloweth in the xix. verſe, and ſo forth
<pb facs="tcp:651:19"/>to the end of the Chapter (for I muſte goe ouer it with ſpeede.) But I demaund, did not Iſrael know god, &amp;c. Paul hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that Iſrael had the word, and yet they were reiected, becauſe they contemned the ſame worde: but this will not ſatiſfie the Iewes, but they wil yet haue an other fling at Paule, and that is this: Thou telleſt vs (ſay they) that notwithſtanding we had the word preached, yet are we reiected iuſtlye, becauſe we heard not with fruite. But tell vs this now: Did not Iſrael know God? Did not Iſrael heare profitably? if thou wilt deny it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> and ſay Iſrael did not know, Dauid wil conuince thee, who ſaith God is known in Iuda, his name is great in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael: but if thou wilt confeſſe that Iſrael did know god, then how canſt thou ſaye truely, that we are caſt off of God, becauſe hauing the word, we brought not forth the fruites thereof: And here they thinke they haue driuen Paule into a ſtraite: but Paul anſwereth this very wel, &amp; in many words. The ſumme of his anſwere is, that there were a few in Iſrael which did he are with fruite and knew god, and they were not
<pb facs="tcp:651:19"/>reiected, neyther doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle here ſpeak of them. But for the moſt parte the Iewes were wicked and rebellious, deſpiſers of god and his word, and therfore were iuſtly caſt off. So then Paul doth anſwere thus: the nations of the Iewes is now cut off by gods iuſtice, that they ſhould not be the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church of god as before: but not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perticular man cut off: for god hath ſtil reſerued vnto him ſelf a number according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of grace, which (no doubt) ſhal be ſaued: I may not if I woulde, nor I neede not if I myght, to ſtand vpon the ſubſtance of this anſwere: namely, to ſhew how it is ſayde, that Iſrael is cut off, and yet god hath his Church in Iſrael: it hath beene handled at large in this Chapter already, but will fall out more playne in the Chapter folowing, as will well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the next Lecture.</p>
            <p>For the manner of his aunſwere, Paul fearing leaſt by telling y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reieciting of the Iewes, he ſhould growe in miſliking and hatred with them, will not anſwere in his own words, but in the wordes of Moſes &amp; Eſay: his firſt place is in <hi>Deut. 32.</hi> ver. <hi>21.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:651:20"/>ſecond and thirde in the beeginning of the <hi>65.</hi> Chapter of Eſaye. There bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe thinges heerein to bee conſidered, which I muſt but name.</p>
            <p>Of the Gentiles hee ſayeth, firſt that they were not a nation, or his nation, doubt leſſe they were a great people, and ſuch a people, as had great authoritie, large do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, &amp; great wealth: And yet becauſe they had not the knowledge &amp; ſeruice of God, Moſes ſaith they be not a people. To teach vs what it is that chiefly is to be com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mended in cities, townes &amp; countries, it is not larg borders, great dominions, ample priuiledges, much wealth, and ſuch like: no theſe were in the heathen, and yet Moſes ſaith, they were not a people, or not Gods people. Dauid doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend Sion not for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth therof,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.1.</note> or much people, or great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges (which things were ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiful in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie) but he doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende it, becauſe there was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tabernacle, there men did aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law read, &amp; expounded, &amp; to do vnto god ſuch ſeruice as he required. I deny not but thoſe things be good, &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great benefit of gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but
<pb facs="tcp:651:20"/>comparable to the hauing and vſe of gods worde, and therefore howſoeuer we do for theſe things, our chiefe care muſt bee that we may inioy the vſe of Gods lawe, for without that wee are not worthie to bee counted the people of God. And let this driue vs to be thankfull vnto God, who hath beſtowed vpon vs this benefite moſte ineſtimable, and hath denied it to other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but I may not proſecute this.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hee ſayth of the Gentiles, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were a fooliſhe nation, doubtles the Iewes were neuer comparable to them in worldly wiſdome, their wit is wondered at euery where, both for finding out what was good and ill in mans life: For loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo neerely into the ſecrete workes of god, for making of very exquiſite lawes, &amp; alſo for many other excellent things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were very wiſe: and yet becauſe they had not the knowledge of God by his worde, therefore doth Moſes call them a fooliſh nation. To teach vs not to ſtande too much vpon our wiſdome, if it be but fleſhly, for all the wiſdome in the worlde if it bee ſeparate from the knowledge of god
<pb facs="tcp:651:21"/>in Chriſte Ieſus, it is but fooliſhnes, as Paule doth affirme.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.19. Sapi. 9.6.</note> And though a man be neuer ſo perfect (ſaith Salomon) among the children of men, yet if the wiſdome of God be not with him he ſhal not be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the gentiles it is ſaid by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſought not after god &amp;c. They knew there was a God, and in their wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they were very diligent to ſeek out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knowledge of that God, but they ſought him not as they ought, they ſought him not in his word, where only he was to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and therfore it is ſaid they ſought him not: and in deede whoſoeuer will ſeek the true knowledge of God any other where then in his worde it is but labour loſt: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a neceſſary leſſon, which Chriſte doth giue to his aduerſaries, and to vs all, Search the ſcriptures,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.39.</note> for in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye thinke to haue eternall life, &amp; theſe are they whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che teſtifie of me. Theſe things I paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lightly, as not directly pertaining to the Apoſtles purpoſe, and yet I touch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they lye in my way, and hereafter I ſhall apply them. And vnto Iſrael hee
<pb facs="tcp:651:21"/>ſaith, All the day long haue I ſtretched foorth my hand, &amp;c. <hi>ver. 21.</hi> Of the gentiles hee hath ſaide, they were not worthie the name of a people, they were fooliſhe, and they ſought not God. Now for Iſrael he ſaith, That God hath ſtretched foorth his hande vnto them, all the day long, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>When hee ſayth God ſtretched foorth his hand, he doth ſet foorth the great care that God had to bryng them to ſaluation, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith (all the day long) hee doth tell vs howe great diligence God did vſe to bring this to paſſe. And when hee ſaith (that Iſrael was a diſobedient, and a gaine ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing people) hee wyll ſet before vs the great negligence and backewardneſſe whiche was in them. Nowe drawe all theſe together, and make one doctrine of them all, it is thus: The negligence and dulneſſe of man in well doing is great: But ſuch is the mercie of GOD to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards man, and ſo careful and diligent is God for man, that all the day, he doeth ſtretche foorth his hande, that is, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually his mercy doeth ſtryue and wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle with our backewardneſſe (if it bee
<pb facs="tcp:651:22"/>poſſible to ouercome it. As we ſee in Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in Cain, and in many others, who when they were fallen from God, they ſought not to God to bee reconciled againe, but God ſought vnto them: yea, and when they hyd themſelues, yet God found them out. But aboue the reſt it is notable to this purpoſe, that is written in the <hi>19.</hi> of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> where it is ſaid, that the angell doth charge Lot and his familie to depart ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily out of Sodom,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.16.</note> and yet they lingered: and the text ſaith, That as they prolonged the time, the men caught both him and his wife, and his two daughters by the handes (the Lord being mercifull vnto him) and he brought him forth, and ſet him without the Citie. See here the backwardneſſe of mans nature in Lot: but chiefly beholde the forwardnes that is in god to ſtriue and wraſtle with man, that by his mercie hee may ouercome mans wickednes. So heere the Iewes are fallen from god, they are rebellious and vnbeleeuing, and yet God doth ſtill offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaluation, he ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth foorth his hand vnto them, hee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth his mercie, he doth it all the day lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.
<pb facs="tcp:651:22"/>Nowe (of all this that the Apoſtle heere ſetteth downe, both of the vntowardnes of the Gentiles, &amp; backwardnes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iewes) let vs conclude with that which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth heere driue vnto, which is the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of God in reiecting the Iewes, &amp; the mercy of God in calling the Gentiles, &amp; that doth appeare thus. The Gentiles are no nation, or not Gods nation, a fooliſhe people, and ſuch a people as ſeek not after God, and yet they are ſaued by gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. To the Iewes God doth ſtreth out his hand, and offer ſaluation ſtill, and yet they continue vnfaithfull &amp; diſobedient, and ſo are caſt of by Gods iuſtice. So then that which we haue here to conclude, &amp; which Paule would haue the Church of Rome to learne of all this that hee ſaieth of the Iewes and gentiles is but this: that the gentiles were called to bee partakers of gods graces, not of their merite, but of gods meere mercie: and therefore all the prayſe and glory of their ſaluation is to be giuen to God alone, and nothing to them ſelues: the reiecting of the Iewes is of gods iuſtice, for their owne wickedneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:651:23"/>And therefore all the blame of that to bee laide vpon themſelues, and nothing at all vpon God. If I coulde or might make of this a generall doctrine, it would teach vs all thus much, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſaluation of all Gods people is of Gods only mercy without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſeruing of man: and that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of all the wicked is of theyr owne deſart onely without any faulte in God: according to that which God ſayth by the Prophet:<note place="margin">Hoſe. 13.9.</note> Thy deſtruction O Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el is thine owne, but thy ſaluation is of me alone. Thus then we ſee that Iſrael dyd heare, that is, had the worde, and yet they were iuſtly reiected of God, becauſe they heard not with fruite, but contemned the worde: and where they thinke they can alledge for themſelues that they were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable hearers, becauſe it is ſaid the knew God, Paule ſaith, that ſome of them knew God, and they were not caſt off, but the moſt part knew not, &amp; were reiected: and for the ſaluation of the gentiles, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer els is ſaued, it is of Gods mercy without mans deſeruing, as alſo the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of the wicked is of gods iuſtice
<pb facs="tcp:651:23"/>through mans wickednes, without any vniuſtice or fault in God. God (for his ſonne Ieſus Chriſtes ſake) continue amongſt vs the vſe of his worde, make vs not idle hearers, but profitable doers of the ſame, giue vs faith and eternall ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the death and merites of Chriſte Ieſus the ſonne of God: To whom, with God the father, and God the holy ghoſte, bee all honour, glory, prayſe, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for euer more.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Imprinted at London at the three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Dawſon, for Thomas Wodcock. 1583.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
